A Guide to the Marcia de Garmo Loudoun County Development Collection, 1933-2008, n.d.
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Marcia de Garmo Loudoun County Development Collection, 1933-2008, n.d.
Thomas Balch Library
M 104, OMB 026, AV 010
5 cubic feet.
The collection contains materials created and collected by Marcia de Garmo in the course of her volunteer work with numerous conservation organizations in and around Loudoun County.
Marcia de Garmo
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
2013.077
Biographical Information
Marcia de Garmo was born to George T. and Kathleen Bell in Washington, DC. George T. Bell was a businessman who also served as a special assistant to President Richard Nixon. Marcia [Bell] de Garmo attended the Potomac and Madeira schools in McLean, Virginia and Wellesley College in Massachusetts. In 1963, she married George J. de Garmo, and together they had two children.
In 1994, the de Garmos relocated from Washington, DC to a rural property in Aldie, VA owned by Marcia's family. At this time, Marcia de Garmo began volunteering with a number of organizations working to stop the rapid development of Loudoun County and to preserve its rural character. She was a founder of the Sustainable Loudoun Network, Co-Founder of the Voters to Stop Sprawl, President of the Virginia League of Conservation Voters, Board Member of the Piedmont Defense Fund, Steering Committee Member of the Route 50 Corridor Coalition, and an active member of a number of other established and ad hoc conservation organizations. Throughout the late 1990s and early 2000s, de Garmo worked with these organizations to improve traffic congestion, amend zoning regulations, reduce pollution, hinder the residential and commercial development of open space and farm land in Loudoun County, as well as to elect "smart growth" candidates to the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors and other offices.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials created and collected by Marcia de Garmo in the course of her volunteer work with numerous local and regional conservation organizations. The collection is divided into two series.
Series I Organizations, 1993-2003, n.d.
The first series contains materials related to organizations in which de Garmo held leadership or membership roles. The materials in this series are related to the administration, management, and everyday work of the organizations. Included are meeting agenda and minutes, financial records, correspondence, membership lists, fundraising materials, promotional materials, notes and other documents. The organizations represented include: Coalition for Leesburg's Future, Coalition for Smarter Growth, Loudoun County Taxpayer Alliance, Piedmont Defense Fund, Piedmont Environmental Council, Route 50 Corridor Coalition, Sustainable Loudoun Network, Virginia League of Conservation Voters, and Voters to Stop Sprawl. These are not the formal records of the organizations. They are materials that de Garmo collected and created in the course of her volunteer work. As such, they are not complete or comprehensive records. Additionally, because many of the organizations had interrelated missions, staffs and budgets, some of the materials pertain to more than one group. For example, Voters to Stop Sprawl was the political action committee formed by Sustainable Loudoun Network and these two organizations held joint meetings. Although efforts have been made to associate the materials with the most relevant organization whenever possible, information relating to both organizations may be found in both locations.
Series II Advocacy, 1933-2008, n.d.
The second series contains documents related to the advocacy of conservation and development issues independent of specific organizations. They consist primarily of research materials, including correspondence, reports, publications, and clippings. In many cases, there is overlap between the materials contained in this series and materials relating to the organizations in Series I. For example, materials related to transportation issues may be found in Series II (Transportation) as well as in Series I (Route 50 Corridor Coalition), among others. Series II is organized by topic. The topics included are: Development Projects; Land Use and Zoning; Loudoun County Government; Transportation; Urban Sprawl and Smart Growth; and Water. The final topic contains de Garmo's notes, which touch on a number of different issues simultaneously. Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Marcia de Garmo Loudoun County Development Collection (M 104), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Washington Post. “Marcia Jean Bell—George DeGarmo III.” June 19, 1963.
Washington Post. “George Bell, 60, Ex-Aide to Nixon.” March 15, 1973.
Related Material
Preservation Society of Loudoun County Collection (M 068); unpublished papers including: “Brief Summary of the History of Land Use Planning in Loudoun County,” by unknown author; “By-pass Middleburg A Subject of Debate,” by Sandra McGushin; “Maryland and Virginia Bypass Alternatives Review Committee Report and Resolution”; “Rural vs. Suburbia: A Question of Controversy in Loudoun County Virginia,” by Christine E. Gates.
Related search terms include: Cities and towns-Growth; Land Use--Virginia; Sustainable development; League of Conservation Voters; Piedmont Environmental Council
Contents List
  - Series I: Organizations 1993-2003, n.d.
    - Coalition for Leesburg's Future 1997, n.d.
    - Coalition for Smarter Growth 1997-2002
    - Loudoun County Taxpayer Alliance 1997, n.d.
    - Piedmont Defense Fund 1997-2000
    - Piedmont Environmental Council 1996-2002, n.d.
    - Piedmont Environmental Council--Studies and Presenatations 1993-2000
    - Piedmont Environmental Council--Comprehensive Plan Revisions 2000
    - Piedmont Environmental Council--Promotional Materials n.d.
    - Route 50 Corridor Coalition 1995-1999
    - Route 50 Corridor Coalition n.d.
    - Route 50 Corridor Coalition--Meeting Attendance 1996-1997, n.d.
    - Route 50 Corridor Coalition--Membership 1996-1998, n.d.
    - Route 50 Corridor Coalition--Route 50 Corridor News 1996-1998
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network 1998
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network 1999-2000
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network n.d.
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network--Dulles Toll Road 1997-1998
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network--"Population, Taxes, Jobs and Pollution--A Position Paper" 2000
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network--Study/Report Data 1995-2000
    - Sustainable Loudoun Network--Web Site n.d.
    - Virginia League of Conservation Voters 2000-2002, n.d.
    - Virginia League of Conservation Voters--Budget 2000-2002
    - Virginia League of Conservation Voters--Elections 2001
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl 2000-2003, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Financial Records 1999-2001, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Fundraising 1999-2003, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Promotional Materials 1999, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Web Site 2002
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Clippings 1999-2003, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidate Endorsements 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidate Questionnaires 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Bill Bogard 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Jim Burton 1995-1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Chuck Harris 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Sally Kurtz 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Patti Morrissey 2001
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Tom Rust 2001
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Scott York 1998-May 1999, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Scott York June 1999-2003, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Candidates--Other 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Phone Bank September-November 1999
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Phone Bank Research n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl--Town Council Elections 1998-May 1999, n.d.
    - Voters to Stop Sprawl Leesburg 2002
  - Series II: Advocacy 1933-2008, n.d.
    - Development Projects--Broad Run Village 1992-November 1997
    - Development Projects--Broad Run Village December 1997-2001
    - Development Projects--Evergreen Rural Village 2001-2003
    - Development Projects--Kirkpatrick Farms 1999-1998
    - Development Projects--Worldcom Corporate Office Headquarters 1998-2001
    - Land Use and Zoning--Adequate Public Facilities Ordinance 1998
    - Land Use and Zoning--Dulles South Area Management Plan 1993-September 1997
    - Land Use and Zoning--Dulles South Area Management Plan October 1997-2000, n.d.
    - Land Use and Zoning--Fiscal Impact Fees 1997
    - Land Use and Zoning--Leesburg Annexation 2002
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun Central Reserve n.d.
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun County Capital Improvement Program 1997-1998
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun County Comprehensive Plan 2000-2001, n.d.
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun County Comprehensive Plan--Clippings 2000-2001
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun County Open Space and Scenic Resources Plan 1995
    - Land Use and Zoning--Loudoun County Zoning Ordinance 2002-2003
    - Land Use and Zoning--Purcellville Urban Growth Area Management Plan--Joint Planning Committee Commission Draft 2005
    - Land Use and Zoning--Purcellville Urban Growth Area Management Plan 2006
    - Land Use and Zoning--School Construction 2000, n.d.
    - Land Use and Zoning--Virginia Zoning Laws and Policies 1996-1998, n.d.
    - Loudoun County Government--County of Loudoun Fiscal Year 2001 Draft Fiscal Plan 2000
    - Loudoun County Government--State of the County Address, 2001 2000
    - Loudoun County Government--Citizen Upate Newsletter 2003
    - Transportation--Reports--Commission on the Future of Transportation in Virginia 1997
    - Transportation--Reports--Route 50 Corridor Study 1995
    - Transportation--Reports--Snickersville Turnpike: A Proposal for Restoration of Rural Historic Road 1995
    - Transportation--Surface Transportation Policy Report (Newsletter) 1996-1998
    - Transportation--Road Construction and Traffic 1997-2000, n.d.
    - Transportation--Western Transportation Corridor 1996-2001
    - Transportation--Sales Tax Referendum 2002, n.d.
    - Urban Sprawl and Smart Growth 1995-2001, n.d.
    - Urban Sprawl and Smart Growth--Clippings 1989-2000
    - Urban Sprawl and Smart Growth--Clippings 2001, n.d.
    - Water--Water Quality 1997-2006
    - Water--Preliminary Report on Groundwater Resources of Northern Virginia by R.C. Cady 1933
    - Water--Comprehensive Plan for Water and Sewerage Facilities, Loudoun County, Virginia April 1970
    - Water--Future Water Supply in Western Loudoun County Virginia-A Feasibility Study of Regionalizing Water Service Requirements to Meet Projected Needs December 1977
    - Water--Report on Western Loudoun Regional Water Supply for the Loudoun County Sanitation Authority December 1983
    - Water--Final Report to the Loudoun County Board of Supervisors from the Task Force for Refuse Disposal June 3, 1985
    - Water--Potomac Water Supply Plan March 1988
    - Water--Ground Water Issue and Solutions in the Potomac River Basin/ Chesapeake Bay Region March 14-16, 1989
    - Water--County-Wide Water Supply Study for Loudoun County, Virginia prepared for Loudoun County Sanitation Authority (1/3) March 1988
    - Water--County-Wide Water Supply Study for Loudoun County, Virginia prepared for Loudoun County Sanitation Authority (2/3) March 1988
    - Water--County-Wide Water Supply Study for Loudoun County, Virginia prepared for Loudoun County Sanitation Authority (3/3) March 1988
    - Water--Groundwater Issues and Solutions March 1989
    - Water--Water or Waste; A Survey of Pertinent Public Documents Compiled for Catoctin Creek Coalition (1/2) November 1989
    - Water--Water or Waste; A Survey of Pertinent Public Documents Compiled for Catoctin Creek Coalition (2/2) November 1989
    - Water--Groundwater Issues and Solutions November 1989
    - Water--Groundwater Resource Investigation/ Hydrogeologic Review, Suitability of Site "P" for Proposed Loudoun County Landfill Facility June 10, 1990
    - Water--Report on the Impact of the Proposed Loudoun County Solid Waste Landfill on the Future Use of the North Fork of Catoctin Creek as a Source of Public Water Supply for the Town of Purcellville, Virginia June 9, 1990
    - Water--Hydrogeology of, and Quality and Recharge Ages of Ground Water in, Prince William County, Virginia 1990-1991
    - Water--Statistical Analysis of Groundwater in Loudoun County. Volume 1: Groundwater Quantity November 1, 1993
    - Water--Interpretive Guide to Geology and Groundwater in Loudoun County Virginia 1993
    - Water--Groundwater Modeling of Western Loudoun County to Demonstrate Recharge Mapping and Wellhead Protection Planning 1996
    - Water--Water and Wastewater Facilities Master Plan [Purcellville, VA] (1/2) April 1996
    - Water--Water and Wastewater Facilities Master Plan [Purcellville, VA] (2/2) April 1996
    - Water--Western Loudoun Water and Wastewater Study(1/2) 1997
    - Water--Western Loudoun Water and Wastewater Study(2/2) 1997
    - Water--Water Resources Study-Purcellville, Virginia March 14, 2000
    - Water--Goose Creek Source Water Protection Program-Volume I: Summary of Program Implementation Approach 2003
    - Water--Goose Creek Source Water Protection Program-Volume II: Technical Support 2003
    - Water--Water Demand Projections and Demand Management July 2007
    - Water--Groundwater Supply Alternatives July 2007
    - Water--Water Resources Study Final Report (1/4) December 2007
    - Water--Water Resources Study Final Report (2/4) December 2007
    - Water--Water Resources Study Final Report (3/4) December 2007
    - Water--Water Resources Study Final Report (4/4) December 2007
    - Water--Water Conservation Plan, Purcellville March 2008
    - Water--Developing Sleeter Lake as Water Supply Alternative April 2008
    - General Notes--Notebook 1997-1999
    - General Notes--Notes 2000-2002, n.d.
  - Sustainable Loudoun Network Smart Growth Forum [VHS] March 23, 2003
  - Piedmont Environment Council 1997
  - Sustainable Loudoun Network 1999
  - Citizen Update(Newsletter) 2003
  - Sales Tax Referendum 2002
  - Urban Sprawl/Smart Growth n.d.